I've got dreams too!
I'm gonna become an even greater
Hokage than you, Dad!
(ナルト)夢だって ちゃんとある。
俺ってば
父ちゃんを超す火影になる！
I swear I will!
ぜってえなるからな。
So when you see Mom over there,
please tell her...
あっちで母ちゃんにも伝えてくれ。
that she doesn't have to
worry about me at all!
俺のことは
全然 心配なんかすんなって。
Tell her I'm doin' my best!
しっかり やってんだって！
aimaina hyouden koshiraete hitatteru no
I create a vague critical biography and wallow in it
seisei saisai nani o mada matteru no
Generation after generation, time after time,
what are you still waiting for
itsunomanika hitori ni natta
I was all alone before I knew it
tameiki hitotsu haite nageite
Breathed out a single sigh and lamented
jounetsu moyashita ano koro o
Those days of burning passion
shinketsu sosoide torimodosunda
Put your heart and soul into getting them back
en de tsunagareba kono hibi mo
Bind these days with bonds and perhaps
suteru hodo koware tenaidarou
They can be salvaged
ayumi o tomenaide
Don't stop walking forward
kibou o sutenaide
Don't give up hope
douka furimuite
Please look back
dou ka kimiyo
Please, if you would
jin jin kokoro ga itamunara
If the heart throbs with pain
kannen no ori o uchiyaburu nda
Break through the ideology that imprisons you
enen tsukihi wa megurukedo
Time goes around for eternity
suteru ni wa yami ga asaidarou
But the darkness within you is still shallow,
not worth throwing it all away
jounetsu moyashita ano koro o
Those days of burning passion
shinketsu sosoide torimodosu nda
Put your heart and soul into getting them back
ai o wakeaeba kono hibi mo
If we love each other then surely these days will
Once again, shine upon you
mouichido kimi o terasudarou
The Final Valley
We're leaving the rest to you...
Kakashi, Sakura...
(ヒルゼン)あとのことは任せたぞ。
Sasuke and Naruto.
カカシ サクラ サスケ ナルト…。
Lord Third!
(カカシ)三代目。
Elder Brother, you finally
settled things with Madara.
(扉間)兄者
これで マダラとの決着もついた。
As Saru said...
let's leave the rest
to the next generation.
あとは サルの言うように
ただ後の者どもに託すとしよう。
Naruto Uzumaki...
《柱間 : うずまきナルト。
Sasuke Uchiha...
うちはサスケ。
You two will probably find
a different conclusion than we did.
お前たちなら 俺たちとは違う
決着もあるだろう。
No... make sure you do.
いや そうなってくれ》
Now, we're free too!
(孫悟空)
これで俺たちは もう自由だ。
I'm going back to Suirendo!
俺は水簾洞に帰るで ウキキィー！
I'm going to seclude myself in a forest.
We can finally go back to our homes.
(穆王)
私は森にこもることにします。
(重明)
やっと俺らも故郷へ帰れんだな。
It's like a dream.
なんか夢見てるみてえだぜ。
Eight Tails, what are you gonna do?
(九喇嘛)
八尾 てめえはどうすんだ？
Me? Well...
(牛鬼)俺か？ 俺はだな…。
I think I'm gonna go back to Bee.
やっぱ
ビーのところへ戻ることにする。
Even his annoying rap
has ended up growing on me.
あいつの耳障りなラップも
クセになっちまってるしな。
So, what about you?
で お前は？
ん？
What will you do?
どうすんだよ？
I'll...
俺はなぁ…。
A little piece of each of your chakra...
(ハゴロモ)お前たち全員のチャクラは→
is already within Naruto.
すでに ナルトの中に
少しずつ入っている。
In short, Naruto is like
a gathering place for you.
ナルトは いわばお前たちの
寄り合い所みたいなものだ。
If you want to discuss something,
you can speak to each other through
your chakra inside Naruto.
何か相談事があれば→
ナルトの中のチャクラで
おのおの話し合える。
Kurama...
Hmm?
九喇嘛。
ん？
I'd like you to stay inside Naruto as
the overseer of the gathering place.
お前は寄り合い所の管理役として
ナルトの中にいてやれ。
It's no longer a hardship
for you anymore, is it?
えっ！
もう 苦ではなかろう。
Well, if you say so, old man,
I guess have no choice.
ま じじいがそう言うなら
しかたねえか。
(みんな)ハハハハ！
何だ!? 何がおかしい！
What?!
What's so funny?
Still not upfront with your feelings...
You haven't changed at all, Kurama.
素直でないところは
相変わらずですね 九喇嘛。
So the Great Ninja War
is finally over now.
ヘヘヘッ。
(サクラ)これでやっと
忍界大戦は終わったんですね。
Yes. All that's left is...
あぁ あとは…。
Naruto and Sasuke...
I asked you before.
ナルトとサスケ
前に わしが問うたな。
After battling my mother Kaguya,
我が母 カグヤと戦い→
is there any change to
the answers you gave me?
己の出した答えに
変化はあったか？
My answer's the same.
And I'm sorry, Super Gramps,
答えは変わんねえ。
ただ 大じいちゃんには悪いけど→
but there is one thing I feel
strongly about after fighting Kaguya...
今回 カグヤってのと戦って思った。
I'm really glad that
Kushina Uzumaki was my mom.
俺の母ちゃんが
うずまきクシナで心底よかったって。
Kaguya was different from
anyone I've ever battled.
カグヤは
今まで戦ったやつらとは違う。
It's like she didn't have a heart at all.
心が ねえみてえな感じだった。
It's said my mother Kaguya started off
as a beloved goddess of the people.
母カグヤも 初めは
民の信望厚き女神だったそうだ。
I do not know for sure what
caused her to transform
鬼と呼ばれるように変貌した
理由はわからぬが…。
into a being that came to
be called a demon.
I suspect something was triggered
the moment she devoured
the Chakra Fruit.
おそらくチャクラの実を
食らったときから→
何かが始まっていたのだろう。
In any case,
you are not like my mother.
どちらにしろ お前は母とは違う。
I trust you not to become like her,
尾獣たちすべてのチャクラを
有していても→
even with all of the Tailed Beast
Chakra within you.
母のようにはなるまいて。
Now then, all that's left is...
to undo the Infinite Tsukuyomi.
さて 残るは
無限月読を解術するだけだ。
But how, specifically?
Do you need our powers?
具体的にはどうやる？
わしたちの力も必要なのか？
No, you're fine.
Naruto has the chakra
of every Tailed Beast.
お前たちはいい。
And Sasuke possesses the Rinnegan.
尾獣すべてのチャクラを持つナルトと→
If they both weave
the sign for rat simultaneously,
輪廻眼を持つサスケが
互いに子の印を結びさえすれば→
the jutsu will be undone.
What? That's it? It's so simple.
術は完全に解ける。
I researched thoroughly how to
undo Mother's Infinite Tsukuyomi.
なんだ 意外と簡単じゃねえか。
かつて母がやった無限月読を
解術するために調べ尽くした。
There's no mistake.
Now then,
the rest is up to you, Sasuke.
間違いない。
して あとは サスケよ。 お前は？
Yes...
But first, I'm executing the current
Five Kage inside the Infinite Tsukuyomi.
(サスケ)そうだな。
だが まずは この無限月読の中→
今の五影どもを処刑する。
What did you just say, Sasuke?
今 なんて言った サスケ？
え？
What about the Five Kage?
五影を… なんだと？
Oh, and...
I'm putting all of you Tailed Beasts
under my control...
それとな 尾獣ども→
and eventually,
I'll get rid of you as well.
お前らはすべて
俺の管理下に置き→
What did you say?!
いずれ処理する。
なんだと！
Kurama!
He put the Tailed Beasts
in a genjutsu...
グッ ウッ…。
九喇嘛！
尾獣たちを幻術に…。
and with a single glance too.
Naruto, it has ended up
as I expected.
ただの一瞥で…。
ナルトよ やはり こうなったな。
I have no choice
but to leave the rest to you.
あとは
お前に任せるしかなくなった。
I cannot stay in
this world any longer.
I shall soon fade away.
わしも この世にいる限界だ。
じきに消える。
Yeah, and sorry for saying this,
Six Paths Super Gramps...
ああ。 これも六道の
大じいちゃんには悪いけど→
but we won't end up like your sons.
大じいちゃんの
子供らみてえにはならねえよ。
I'm not Ashura.
And Sasuke isn't Indra either.
俺はアシュラじゃねえ。
Sasuke!
Is this what your current dream is?
それに サスケは
インドラってやつでもねえ！
サスケ それが
今のお前の夢だってのか！
Are you saying you're
still seeking vengeance?
まだお前は復讐を
望んでいるっていうのか？
Sasuke!
I admit, at one time,
all I wished for was destruction,
サスケ君！
確かに かつては ただ破壊を望み
復讐だけが目的だった。
and vengeance was my goal.
But I feel differently now.
I want to destroy, and rebuild.
だが今は違う。
破壊し そして創り直すのさ。
A village no longer
shrouded in darkness.
I'll reform the shinobi world.
闇を抱えぬ里。 忍世界を一新する。
What I'm touting is...
グッ…。
俺が掲げるもの それは…。
... revolution!
Revolution?!
革命だ！
革命… だと？
My dear Sasuke,
what do you want to do?
((サスケよ お前は何がしたい？
What is it that you seek
in the aftermath of this war?
この戦いの果てに 何を望む？
I want to hear your honest thoughts
and opinions.
(お前の正直な考えを聞きたい))
All of the previous Kage created
these current circumstances.
((今までの影たちが
この状況を作った。
So I will become Hokage
and change the village.
(だから俺が火影になり
里を変える))
This Hokage you speak of...
What do you mean by it?
((そのお前のいう火影とは
どういう意味だ？
If you want to know so badly,
I'll tell you.
(そんなに知りたきゃ教えてやる))
Catastrophic Planetary Devastation!
地爆天星！
あぁっ！
Naruto...
It's on you!
ナルト… 頼む！
I swear
I'll get you all out!
俺が 必ず 助け出す！
Just hang in there
a little while longer!
少しの間 辛抱してくれ！
Because of this war,
I've become quite adept at
using my Rinnegan's abilities.
この戦争で 輪廻眼の能力と
使い方も ずいぶんと慣れた。
And all those who were
in my way are gone.
そして 邪魔者は いなくなった。
Except for you...
Naruto.
お前以外はな！ ナルト。
Things just don't go as planned.
When I bequeathed power
to just one side,
(ハゴロモ)うまく いかぬものだ。
力を一方に託した結果が
かつての インドラとアシュラ…。
I ended up with Indra and Ashura.
This time, even after entrusting power
to both, the result is the same.
そして 両方に託した結果も
今や 同じ…。
ふぅ…。
Nope... All sibling squabbling
ends right here!
いや 兄弟ゲンカは
ここで 終わりにするってばよ。
Let the Tailed Beasts go.
They've finally gained freedom.
尾獣たちを放してやってくれ。
あいつらは
やっと 自由になれたんだ。
I'm friends with them, so I know.
あいつらと仲よくなったから
わかんだ。
They won't cause trouble anymore.
Naruto, you don't seem to get it.
もう 悪さはしねえよ。
ナルト！
お前 わかってないようだな。
You're now the Jinchuriki
of all the Tailed Beasts.
Which means I plan to
eventually get rid of
今や お前は
尾獣たち全員の人柱力だ。
もちろん
お前の中の尾獣のチャクラも→
the Tailed Beast Chakra
inside of you too.
のちのち すべて
始末するつもりだ。
What?!
そんな…。
In other words,
you're going to die, Naruto.
つまり お前は死ぬんだ ナルト。
Out of necessity.
必然的にな。
If what the Sage said was true,
there's no need to use
仙人が言ったとおりなら
無限月読を解くのに→
the Tailed Beast power inside you
to release the Infinite Tsukuyomi.
そもそも お前の中の尾獣の力を
使う必要はないだろ。
I can take advantage of
the Tailed Beasts that I captured.
I'll let them live until then.
俺が捕まえた尾獣どもを
利用すればな…。
You know that I won't
let you do that, right?
やつらも それまでは
生かしておいてやる。
俺が そうさせねえの
わかってるよな？
I guess I'll have to
deal with you first, Naruto.
やはり… まずは お前か ナルト。
Let's move this elsewhere.
You know, don't you?
場所を変える。
お前なら わかっているな？
Wait, Sasuke!
Sensei!
(カカシ)待て サスケ！
うぅ…。
先生！
The lingering aftereffects
of the Sharingan...
《写輪眼の影響が まだ…》
I...
I know in my heart that
there's nothing I can do!
私は！ 私にはどうすることも
できないって本当はわかってる。
Even though I love you.
Even though I care about you
so much, Sasuke. And yet...
大好きなのに サスケ君を
こんなに思ってるのに。
I can't get close to you
or exchange blows with you.
寄り添うことも
刺し違えることもできずに→
I can only whine and beg
and cry like this again.
こうやって また駄々こねて
泣くことしかできない。
It's so pitiful, isn't it?
みっともないよね ほんと。
Sakura...
Thank you.
((サクラ…。
(ありがとう))
But... But Sasuke!
If there's even a little corner of
your heart that thinks about me,
でも でも サスケ君！
少しでも 少しでも私のことが
心の隅っこにあるなら→
please don't leave again!
お願い
もう遠くに行かないで！
If we stick together,
I know it can be like old times again...
ずっと一緒にいれば
いつか 昔みたいに…。
You're...
... really annoying.
お前は 本当にうざいな。
Sakura!
You didn't need to put Sakura
under genjutsu!
サクラ！
If I didn't,
サクラちゃんに幻術まで
かけることはねえだろうが。
she would've chased after us,
and gotten in the way.
このままじゃ こいつは
俺たちを追ってくるだろう。
Sakura... Sakura just wanted
to help you, all this time.
邪魔になる。
サクラは サクラはお前を
助けたかったんだ ずっと。
So you're suggesting
I enjoy a little romance?
Well, I have no reason to love her
or be loved by her.
恋愛ごっこでも楽しめってのか？
俺には こいつを好く道理も
好かれる道理もない。
The only time you need a reason
is when you hate someone!
理由があるのは
人を嫌いになるときだけでいい。
And Sakura's not trying to
make you hers!
それにサクラは今 お前を
自分のものにしたいんじゃない。
She just wants to help you!
She almost died
by your hand.
ただ お前を助けたいんだ。
But she still thinks of your welfare
and sheds tears for you...
お前に殺されかけたこともある
この子が→
今でもお前のことを思い
涙を流すのは→
because she suffers from loving you!
お前を愛して苦しんでいるからだ。
Mom...
((母さん。
ん？
How does Dad really feel
about Big Brother and me?
父さんは兄さんや俺のこと
本当はどう思ってんのかな？
What makes you ask that
out of the blue?
どうしたの？ 急に。
The other day, he said to me,
"That's my boy."
この前 父さん俺のことを→
He usually says that to Big Brother,
so I was really happy.
さすが 俺の子だって
言ってくれたんだ。
いつもは兄さんに
そう言ってたから→
すごい嬉しかったんだ。
Is that so? That's nice.
But recently, Dad and Big Brother
haven't been getting along, so...
そう よかったじゃない。
でも最近 父さんと兄さんの
仲がよくないから…。
I thought maybe I'm just
a stand-in for Big Brother...
俺は ただ兄さんの
代わりなのかなって。
Your brother is your brother,
and you are you.
兄さんは兄さん
あなたは あなたよ。
Your father is always
thinking about the both of you.
父さんは いつも
あなたたちのことを→
Then why is it always
about Big Brother?!
心配しているわ。
じゃあ なんで兄さんばっかり。
That's not the case.
Your father represents our clan,
そうじゃないわ ただ父さんはね→
and he's expected to
protect the Uchiha Clan.
一族の代表として うちは一族を→
So what?
守らなきゃいけない立場にあるの。
It's just that Itachi is older than you,
and your senior.
それがなんなの？
So he's given more duties
relating to the clan.
イタチは あなたより
大きくて先輩なだけ。
その分 一族のための仕事を
任されるようになるでしょ。
Since your father
oversees those duties,
父さんは
その仕事の監督役だから→
it's only natural that his eyes
will be more focused on Itachi.
どうしたって その目が イタチに→
But this is just between us...
いきがちだったのかも
しれないわね。
When your father is with me,
all he talks about is you.
でも ここだけの話→
私と話すときは
あなたのことばかり→
話してるのよ 父さん。
He's always so serious,
and just not very good at
expressing his feelings.
ただ あの人→
いつも
ムスッとして 不器用だからね。
Here's your lunch, Sasuke.
When you come home,
I'll watch over your shuriken practice.
はい サスケ お弁当。
手裏剣のお稽古なら→
It's not practice. It's training.
帰ってから
母さんが見てあげるから。
I'm leaving!
お稽古じゃない 修業だよ。
Have a great day.
(いってきます。
いってらっしゃい))
Perhaps, those are the ties
to a failed past.
それが
失敗した過去の縛りなのかもな。
Sasuke!
I made a promise.
《サスケ…》
Long ago... to Sakura.
約束したんだ。
昔 サクラちゃんと。
I'll definitely bring Sasuke back!
((サスケは ぜってぇ
俺が連れて帰る。
I swear on my life!
Sensei! You know about
my Ninja Way, right?
(一生の約束だってばよ))
先生 俺の忍道は
もう知ってんだろ？
I'm gonna go.
行ってくっぜ。
Yeah... We're counting on you.
ああ 頼んだぞ。
Love is a difficult thing...
(ハゴロモ)愛情とは難しいものだな。
I once had two sons.
かつて わしにも
２人の子がいた。
I loved them both,
and they loved and revered me.
２人を愛し
２人もわしを敬愛していた。
But I entrusted everything
to the younger brother.
だが兄弟の弟だけに
すべてを託したゆえ→
That became the impetus
for the older brother to begin
hating his brother and me.
それを機に 兄はわしと
その弟を憎むようになり→
Love transformed into hate.
愛情が憎しみへと
変わってしまったのだ。
What molded the current Sasuke,
is none other than
his loss of love in the past.
今のサスケを形作ったのは→
過去の愛情の
喪失からくるものに他ならない。
Madara was the same too.
マダラも そうだった。
Are you saying that Sasuke shares
the same fate as Madara?
サスケも マダラと同じ運命だと
そうおっしゃりたいのですか？
No, not at all.
I, too, want to make the future
better in my own way.
そうではない
わしも己なりに→
Having learned from past mistakes,
this time I gave both of them the power.
未来は
よりよいものにしたいのだ。
かつての過ちから学んでな。
今回は２人に
同じように力を託した。
The past does not exist
to remind the present that
the future cannot change.
過去は 未来が変わらぬと→
The past is supposed to exist
for the sake of the future.
気づかせるために
あるのではなく→
How did you see the potential
within Naruto?
未来のためにあるはずだ。
なぜ ナルトに
可能性を見いだしたのです？
Naruto Uzumaki...
うずまきナルト。
The boy was able to save
and befriend Kurama,
あの子は
憎しみの塊になってしまった→
who had become
a concretion of hatred.
九喇嘛を救い 友となった男だ。
I shall let Naruto handle this.
ナルトに任せてみるとしよう。
Since I hope that hate can be
transformed into love this time.
今度は 憎しみが
愛情へと変わるのを願いながら。
Or rather, I have hope that
love can be regained.
いや 愛情を
取り戻させると願おう。
Because, unlike my mother,
Naruto as well as Sasuke...
(ハゴロモ)サスケも カグヤとは違い
愛が何かを知っている者だ。
know what love is.
ナルトと同じようにな。
This place, huh?
I should've figured.
Doesn't it bring back memories,
Sasuke?
やっぱここかよ
懐かしいな サスケ。
Long ago, we fought here.
昔 ここでやり合ったな
そういやよ。
And just like before,
you're going to lose.
前と同じだ
ここでまたお前が負ける。
You won't be hitting me with
that same punch as last time!
あのときと同じ拳は
もうくらわねえよ。
I'm not about to let you get away
with whatever you want.
それに お前の好き勝手には
させねえ。
I won't let you become
the Hokage, either!
火影だって
お前にゃ渡せねえ。
You don't even understand
what it means to be Hokage!
お前は 火影がなんなのか
まるでわかってねえ。
I told you, that to me,
being Hokage means revolution.
It's totally different from what you think.
言ったな 革命だと。
俺の言う火影は
お前のそれと まったく違う。
Let me tell you something
your big brother said...
お前の兄ちゃんが言ったことを
教えてやる。
It's not the one who
becomes Hokage
who gets acknowledged by all.
火影ってのは→
But it's the one acknowledged by all
who becomes Hokage.
火影になったやつが
認められるんじゃなく→
みんなに認められたやつが
火影になるんだってよ。
I learned not from Itachi's words,
but from the way he lived his life.
俺はイタチの言葉ではなく
生き様からすべてを悟った。
You and I came up
with different answers.
お前と俺では
出した答えが違う。
Let me clarify this
before we battle...
戦う前に はっきりさせるか。
I'll teach you exactly what being
Hokage means to me.
俺の言う火影とは何なのか
教えてやる。
boku ni wa wakaru nda uso o tsuite iru kimi ga
I can tell when you're lying
naite ii yo koko ni zutto irukara
It's okay to cry because I'll always be here
sekaijuu ni koborete iru hontou no ai no kimochi
Feelings of true love spills out throughout the world
sagashidashite miushinatte yoake ga kuru no matteru
We search for it but lose it, while waiting for daybreak
migi no hoshi ni wa boku no namae o tsukete
The star on the right will bear my name
kimi ga yonde okureyo
Will you call out to it?
hidari no hoshi ni wa kimi no namae ga ne
The star on the left will bear your name
niau yo zutto soba ni irukara
It's perfect, because we'll always be together
Next Episode
You don't understand the way
Itachi lived his life at all!
Itachi is now in my past.
I will cut off everything
in my past right here...
Starting with cutting you down.
Yours will be
the last blood I shed...
in the memory
of my late older brother.
Next time on Naruto Shippuden: "The Final Battle"
The Final Battle
I won't let you!